Boker Tov בוקר טוב. Boker Tov. So today's Daf דף Daf is
Zayin ז׳ Zayin and we pick up on the
very bottom of Vav Amud Bet ו׳ עמוד ב׳ Vav Amud Bet
and we have introduced the idea that you need two and the
third one is even a Tefach טפח, Tefach, a position of Rabbi
Shimon רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon that three and a Tefach טפח. Tefach.
Mostly the Gemara גמרא Gemara has been focusing on that difference in
terms of technical derivations from the word Sukkah סוכה Sukkah in the
Pasuk פסוק. Pasuk. But there was also an indication of a deeper
issue at stake when it introduced the idea of the verse from
Yeshayahu ישעיהו Yeshayahu about a God's protection, God's canopy protecting also from
the storms and the word Sukkah סוכה Sukkah and to what degree
Sukkah סוכה Sukkah also is not just for Tzel צל Tzel shade
but general protection. So that's an idea we'll get back to. But
now we're seeing the idea of two and a Tefach טפח Tefach
which is how we rule. The question is going to be where
does that
Tefach טפח Tefach go? So the Gemara גמרא Gemara says like this:
ואותה טפח היכן מעמידה? Ve-ota tefach heichan mamidoh? Two lines from the
bottom. Where do you put that extra Tefach טפח Tefach in order
to, obviously the question is in order to make the structure look
somewhat more house-like,
more it can't be a random Tefach טפח Tefach somewhere. אמר רב
מעמידה כנגד היוצא. Amar Rav mamidoh keneged ha-yotze. The most obvious answer.
You put it in the beginning as the beginning of the third
wall opposite the protrusion. Meaning if you look at Rashi רש״י Rashi
there on the left you see two scenarios of it. But basically
you have two walls perpendicular and the third one starts contiguous and
is the beginning of a third wall so that already suggests the
idea of
surrounded. Two wouldn't suggest the idea of surrounded. The beginning of a
third you finish it in your mind and you see that you
can sort of square it off and you see what the parameters
are and it suggests the idea of being encompassed by walls. So
that's a pretty reasonable position. Nobody is saying you actually try to
substitute the third wall, make it actually physically function as that, but
it suggests the beginning of the third wall. That's what Rav רב
Rav says. אמרי רב כהנא ורב אסי לרב. Amrei Rav Kahana ve-Rav
Assi le-Rav. Rav Kahana רב כהנא Rav Kahana and Rav Assi רב
אסי Rav Assi asked Rav רב: Rav: יעמידנה כנגד היוצא כנגד ראש
תור? Yamidenna keneged ha-yotze, keneged rosh tor? Why don't you put it
opposite the head of a line? That's literally what Rosh Tor ראש
תור Rosh Tor means. But Rashi רש״י Rashi says it means the
way it looks at the end of when you do a furrow,
which basically is obviously at some degree when they ended a furrow
making the furrows in the field somehow it would turn at an
angle. So the question is what exactly is he suggesting? The picture
in Rashi רש״י Rashi shows that pretty obvious, why not try if
you're trying to invisibly end a line, it's easier to invisibly end
a line if you basically start a
triangle. So you do it there
so you can imagine it like that. And that even creates a
greater sense of surrounded. You don't have to imagine two virtual lines.
There are those that want to say that it's even a more
interesting suggestion which is yes, put it on that line but put
it here. So if you're putting it there that's even more for
the space in between some suggestion of sort of being surrounded. But
of course that would suggest a triangular Sukkah סוכה Sukkah which is
not a natural Sukkah סוכה Sukkah and we can understand why Rav
רב Rav did not want to go there because he said that
even though you're only using a little bit, still the model is
a regular rectangular Sukkah סוכה. Sukkah. שתיק רב. Shatik Rav. But Rav
רב Rav didn't have a response.
Presumably yeah you could see trying to sort of make it a
triangle but that wasn't Rav's רב's Rav approach. איתמר נמי, Itmar nami,
it was said also, אמר שמואל משמיה דלוי: Amar Shmuel mishme d'Levi:
מעמידה כנגד היוצא. Mamidoh keneged ha-yotze.
So even though Rav רב Rav did not have a response, nevertheless
that's going to be the consensus opinion. You put it opposite the
protrusion which means the beginning of the next wall
in the normal perpendicular direction. וכן מורין בבי מדרשא. Veken morin be-bei
midrashah.
And that's also how they rule in the house of study. That's
always fascinating when it has this sort of sense of like a
consensus of the Rabbis without it being a particular named opinion. That's
the general Psak פסק Psak that people that's where they say to
put it is you put it perpendicular. I have to tell you
this idea וכן מורין בבי מדרשא Veken morin be-bei midrashah is it
like a hypothetical ruling or were these practical cases really coming
up? Some have speculated that maybe the reason for a lot of
these discussions was because it was hard to find building materials so
you had to sort of really get down to the bare minimum
of what was needed. I remember that we had a student in
the Yeshiva ישיבה Yeshiva a few years back that every Motzei Yom
Kippur מוצאי יום כיפור Motzei Yom Kippur he would forage for building
materials for his Sukkah סוכה Sukkah like find out things that people
threw out on the yard like things that were waiting to be
picked up, big planks of wood or whatever and he would always
have questions for me which is like how to construct it with
like two and a half walls. Things that I figured was in
the Gemara גמרא, Gemara, it was in the Shulchan Aruch שולחן ערוך,
Shulchan Aruch, nobody would ever in real life ask me these questions.
No, he had these questions. How can you construct it with the
minimum building materials? So that's what they anyway ruled in the Beis
Medrash בית מדרש Beis Medrash like Rav רב Rav that you do
the beginning of the third wall in a normal perpendicular fashion. Okay.
רב סימון ואיתימא רב יהושע בן לוי אומר, Rav Simon ve-isema Rav
Yehoshua ben Levi omer, Rav Simon רב סימון Rav Simon and some
say Rav Yehoshua ben Levi רב יהושע בן לוי Rav Yehoshua ben
Levi say. עושה לו טפח שוחק. oseh lo tefach socheik. You make
a laughing טפח, tefach, not a precise טפח. tefach. What does that
mean? It means when you laugh, right, your hand, like your fingers
separate a little bit from one another. And therefore טפח tefach is
four fingers, not four fingers pressed together tightly, but four fingers a
little bit separate, meaning a טפח tefach and a little bit. Okay,
that's the way you've heard of that as a laughing טפח. tefach.
What's the significance of that?
So, עושה לו טפח שוחק ומעמידו בפחות משלושה טפחים סמוך לדופן. oseh
lo tefach socheik u-maamido be-pachos mi-shlosha tefachim samuch la-dofen. And you put
it within three near the wall, וכל טפחים וכל פחות משלושה סמוך
לדופן כלבוד דמי. ve-chol tefachim ve-chol pachos mi-shlosha samuch la-dofen ke-lavud dami.
And anything within three is like it's an appendage, it's like it
is connected. So what is he saying you do? He agrees with
רב Rav that you basically do a rectangular thing. But he wants
to get a little bit more of a wall, so he says
you make it like this, you make it a like a 1.1
טפח. tefach. You put it within a little bit less than three,
you put it within 2.9 טפחים tefachim of the wall. Okay, I
don't think that's to scale, but anyway, okay. And therefore, right, and
therefore so this is your טפח, tefach, that's לבוד. lavud. So now
you've got a wall that is four טפחים. tefachim. Why? So you
actually have part using לבוד, lavud, your actual extension goes four טפחים,
tefachim, not just a טפח. tefach. It goes a little bit further.
What's the significance of four? Four usually is significant as four אמות.
amos. Here the significance of four טפחים tefachim is that the size
of a minimum סוכה sukkah is
right, ראשו רובו ושולחנו, rosho rubo ve-shulchano, which we basically say is
about seven and a half טפחים. tefachim. So four is the majority
of that. Okay, so actually a little less than four is the
majority of that. So he basically says is here, when you got
if you got if you were to add another, I should've probably
done it in a different color just for the virtual, okay, so
if you were to do another
another three and a half, this would be your minimum size סוכה.
sukkah. Okay, you see that? Right? 'Cause you've got your one and
the לבוד lavud is four,
and if you and that's already the majority of a wall which
would be enough to create a minimum sized סוכה. sukkah. So that
makes it a lot easier to view it as you have a
kosher סוכה sukkah because you already have the majority of the third
wall needed for a minimum סוכה. sukkah. And once this is the
kosher סוכה, sukkah, obviously you could fit in the entire amount, but
it allows this to be considered creating a סוכה sukkah because you've
already got the majority of the third wall needed for a minimum
סוכה. sukkah. Okay, so that is the idea.
I did that pretty quickly, but people get that? Yeah? Okay. Alright,
so now let's take a look.
Okay, אמר רב יהודה סוכה העשויה כמבוי כשרה. Amar Rav Yehuda sukkah
ha-asuyah ke-mavoi kesherah. Now that was an easy case. That was when
your original two walls were perpendicular. What if your original two walls
are like an alleyway, are parallel? Yeah, I'm gonna let you let
you do a סוכה sukkah with two and a bit even if
the two main walls are parallel, made like an alleyway, like a
מבוי. mavoi. וההוא טפח מעמידו, ve-hahu tefach maamido, but where do you
put that טפח? tefach? בכל רוח שירצה be-chol ruach she-yirtzeh opposite any
one of the four walls. Meaning, he is basically similar to רב's
Rav's original position. He's basically saying you've got your alleyway, you can
all you have to do is start it start it here, you
start it here, I shouldn't've gotta use a different color well whatever
anyway you could start it here, you could start it here. Any
one of those four directions you want start any one of those
four of those corners you want to start it in, you start
it, but that's enough to be good. Okay, which is pretty funny
because that looks a lot less that suggests a lot less, I
would say, you know, than actual structure than when you start with
a perpendicular. But that's what he says.
Which part of the סוכה sukkah would be kosher? The entire part!
Because the whole סוכה sukkah is surrounded, right, don't get confused here
that because I this is the majority of of a fourth wall.
That's just to give significance to the wall. But the חידוש chiddush
is the entire סוכה sukkah is kosher because it has two and
a bit, but it's the entire סוכה sukkah that's kosher. So here
too the entire סוכה sukkah is kosher, right, even if you've got
these two parallel walls, even if that's just a little bit. Now
the problem with this is because these could be very distant, right?
Let's say these are, you know, 20 feet apart. You know, how
does that work? Here at least you've got the sense that it
sort of squares off the two dimensions and you know what the
dimensions are. Here sort of, you know, you don't really know at
any stage, you know, until you virtually finish it what the actual
dimensions are and what sort of where where it goes. But that's
his חידוש, chiddush, that that would work. Okay,
כלבוד
דמי. ke-lavud dami. So it says like this, I'm sorry, did I?
Where am I? רבי סימון ואיתימא רבי יהושע בן לוי אומר, Rabbi
Simon ve-isai-meira Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi omer, Rabbi Simon and some say
Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi say: עושה לו פס ארבעה ומשהו. oseh lo
pas arba-ah u-mashehu.
No, no, no, no, no. If you've got parallel walls, one טפח
tefach isn't going to be enough. You're going to need to take
a
four
טפח tefach wall ומעמידו בפחות משלושה סמוך. u-maamido be-pachos mi-shlosha samuch. Anything.
So he said, look, buddy, if you want this case to work,
the parallel case, a little טפח tefach isn't going to be enough.
What you're going to need is you're going to need this to
be four, 4.1 let's say. Okay, then you put, then here the
break is 2.9,
so you say לבוד, lavud, so you basically have seven, which is
the minimum size of the סוכה. sukkah. So even without the special
idea of a טפח, tefach, right here the idea is conceptually, you,
it's good even though in practice it's obviously not the entire third
wall, right, but a טפח tefach tells you you can be representative.
What he's saying here is if you had a piece of 4.1
and then you said לבוד, lavud, you don't need any special הלכה
halacha yet of the third wall being a טפח. tefach. Normal הלכות
halachot of walls would say you say לבוד, lavud, that's a normal
wall הלכה, halacha, then you get seven טפחים, tfachim, right? Yes? And
that's the size of, people here with me? Yeah. And that'd be
the size, well, seven אמה משהו, ammah shehu, whatever, it's more than
seven. But anyway, that's the size of a minimum סוכה sukkah wall,
so you actually would then have this without yet the laws of
טפח tefach would translate into this. Okay? With just the laws of
לבוד, lavud, putting something a four טפחים tfachim and a bit within
two and a little less than three translates into two legitimate walls.
However long this is and a seven טפח tefach wall, which is
the minimum size of a real legitimate סוכה sukkah wall. So am
I being clear? When you just say a טפח, tefach, right, you're
even when you say לבוד lavud you only get four, right, here.
You don't get... so that's the חידוש. chidush. The חידוש chidush is
that the third wall can be a טפח, tefach, it doesn't have
to be a legitimate wall. It can be a טפח tefach wall.
It's only a question of what's the best placement. But it doesn't
have to become a real wall. He's saying, no, when you've got
parallel, you need there to be a real wall being created at
the perpendicular. And the only way you're going to get a real
wall created at the perpendicular is not with a טפח, tefach, it's
with four טפחים tfachim and a bit plus לבוד. lavud. That'll create
a real wall at the perpendicular. Okay? Yeah. And now the גמרא's
Gemara going to ask why are the two cases different. So let's
take a look.
Why are we saying seven is a real wall? Because... yeah, it's
really... it's really more like seven. It's seven
אמה משהו, ammah shehu, so... just... just assume seven, just for simplicity.
So assume we're going to get this, but how many times can
you apply this wall of this rule of extension? Do you have
a picket fence? Yes, you can. Yep. Yeah, you can do it
sort of many, many times. So we'll actually... we'll get to it
a little bit... we will be getting to that a little bit
today. Okay, so גמרא Gemara says like this. Yeah. This טפח שוחק
tefach sochek is a picket fence, right? Um,
yeah, but you can have even less, and even like on שבת,
Shabbos, in theory you can just have posts every... what I did
for my סוכה sukkah once, when in the... we had these old...
the canvas ones and they were flapping in the wind and the
question was would it really... by רוח מצויה ruach metzuyah would it
sort of stay, you know, and was it a real wall? Is
I... I take some string, some simple, you know, yarn or whatever,
and I just made it to go from one post to the
next every 2.9 טפחים. tfachim. So you do it like four times
and that's your wall, right? So you can say לבוד lavud even
between strings until you get a 10 טפח tefach wall. You can
do it on the horizontal and you can do it on the
vertical. All right? People do that just in case strings are... exactly.
So yeah, and now actually on some of the סוכות sukkot they
sell that, they sell the סוכות sukkot with these straps that you
pull from one post to the other so whatever happens to the
canvas or whatever you got your halachic wall. All right. So anyway.
But here, so לבוד lavud is not a special טפח tefach הלכה,
halacha, לבוד lavud is a general הלכה halacha and he's saying you
need to create a legitimate perpendicular wall. So the גמרא Gemara says
like this.
Okay. Um, so the גמרא Gemara says, ומאי שנא התם דקא סגי
טפח שוחק? U-mai shna hatam de-kasagai tefach sochek? Why in the perpendicular
case is it enough to have this laughing טפח tefach and, you
know, so at the end result even with לבוד lavud you only
got four? ומאי שנא הכא, U-mai shna hacha, the case, בעי פס
ארבעה? baya pas arba? And why here do you need really a
plank of four? Why here do you really need a... to create
a real seven טפח tefach full legitimate wall? So the גמרא Gemara
gives the obvious answer. התם דאיכא שתי דפנות כהלכתן, Hatam de-ika shtei
defanot ke-hilchasan, there you have two walls as is, you know, correct,
the appropriate meaning perpendicular, they're connected and they basically outline, you know,
already begin to create the shape of a סוכה, sukkah, סגי ליה
בטפח שוחק. sagai lei be-tefach sochek. Then once... that's where we say
the basic הלכה halacha of one טפח. tefach. One טפח tefach against
the wall, a laughing טפח tefach within three טפחים tfachim of the
wall, but it's basically the הלכה halacha of a טפח tefach when
you start with two real perpendicular walls. הכא דליכא שתי דפנות, Hacha
de-leka shtei defanot, here you don't start with two connected walls, you're
starting with two parallel walls, so you can't get started unless you've
got a real two connected walls in reality. אי איכא פס ארבעה
אין, I-ika pas arba in, only if you make it a plank
of four with לבוד lavud gets you seven. okay, and then you
really are starting with two connected perpendicular walls. ואי לא לא, ve'i
lo lo, and if not, not, and if anything less than that
wouldn't work. So here it's saying, yeah, it's not so obvious you
can use a טפח tefach with parallel walls. You want to do
parallel walls, you have to basically turn it into perpendicular walls. Got
to get one, you've got to get create a wall that's at
least seven טפחים tefachim in the other direction. Okay. אמר רבא, Amar
Rava, ואינה ניתרת אלא בצורת הפתח. ve'eina niteres ela b'tzuras hapesach. Now
רבא Rava again is so fascinating, right? Because we start by just
saying a טפח. tefach. We start by an innocent question of okay,
what's the best placement for the טפח? tefach? But then you start
getting people pulling back, right? Being getting a little bit more anxious
with the idea that one טפח tefach is really going to do
it. So the first sort of real pull back, not in the
parallel case, that might not even have been the intended case. But
the first real pull back is the case of that you need
to do it within three and create, turn the one into a
four. That was the first like pull back conceptually from the idea
that one טפח tefach is really enough by itself. רבא Rava now
represents another pull back. He wants to introduce with the טפח tefach
an idea of a צורת הפתח. tzuras hapesach. Right? Everybody knows what
a צורת הפתח tzuras hapesach is, right? No, I'm sorry, okay. I
should not have said that. I'm sorry. You got two posts and
basically it's the shape of a door frame. Two vertical posts and
a horizontal post on top of it. That's how we make an
עירוב. eruv. What we call an עירוב, eruv, right, is we basically
do so, you know, the what do you call it? The yeah,
the electric wire serves as the post on top. You can't use
the electricity posts
for the posts underneath because the wire goes alongside and it has
to go on top. So they basically bang a like two by
four or whatever, you know, against the bottom of the pole that's
ten טפחים tefachim high. And if it's directly under the wire, you
use the idea of the magic extending wall and it goes all
the way up to the top. Okay, but the צורת הפתח tzuras
hapesach is this idea of two poles with something not alongside but
something on top of it. Halachically, that basically is like a door.
Well, you know, a door is part of a wall. So because
it becomes a door, it actually becomes part of a wall. That's
how the whole עירוב eruv idea works is we're surrounded by doorways.
All right, so that's how the עירוב eruv idea works. So a
צורת הפתח tzuras hapesach becomes a door which becomes a wall. So
that's a general הלכה halacha about walls. So רבא Rava wants to
say one טפח tefach isn't going to do it, really. One טפח,
tefach, that's not enough. No, what you need to do is you
need to combine that idea of a טפח tefach with a צורת
הפתח. tzuras hapesach. Basically create more wall as your third wall. And
there're going to be three variations of what רבא Rava is saying.
So let's take a look. So first רבא Rava says, אמר רבא,
Amar Rava, ואינה ניתרת אלא בצורת הפתח. ve'eina niteres ela b'tzuras hapesach.
So the way רש״י Rashi and תוספות Tosafos explains this is that
רבא Rava is saying it's not really about a טפח. tefach. It
really is about that טפח tefach being used as a צורת הפתח,
tzuras hapesach, which means what? So, so he basically says this is
really a radical re-understanding. He says we don't really mean a טפח.
tefach. What we really mean is you have a post here and
a post here and a post on top. And when we say
a טפח, tefach, it's because you know this post is a half
of a טפח tefach and this post is a half of a
טפח, tefach, but really what you're doing is you're sealing off the
whole third wall with a צורת הפתח. tzuras hapesach. Okay, so רבא
Rava really does not like the idea of the טפח tefach doing
it. He wants to translate the טפח tefach as a צורת הפתח.
tzuras hapesach. That's one version of רבא. Rava. איכא דאמרי, Ika d'amri,
there are two other versions of רבא. Rava. איכא דאמרי, Ika d'amri,
some say אמר רבא, Amar Rava, וניתרת נמי בצורת הפתח. uniteres nami
b'tzuras hapesach. No, that what רבא Rava is saying is that I'm
not saying that you need to turn it into a צורת הפתח.
tzuras hapesach. What I'm saying is wherever you use that טפח, tefach,
whether you put your טפח tefach here or whether you're going to
put your טפח tefach over here, the two possibilities, if instead of
a טפח tefach you want to do a צורת הפתח, tzuras hapesach,
you know, that's also a legitimate alternative. Okay, so instead of the
טפח, tefach, you can also do a צורת הפתח tzuras hapesach instead,
which isn't much of a חידוש chiddush because a צורת הפתח tzuras
hapesach always counts as a wall. Okay, a cross beam from one
corner to another corner
diagonally, would that count as a wall? Yeah, yeah, that would. Yes,
you don't have to make a סוכה sukkah with perpendicular walls. That
would be okay, you could just run the cross... Oh, a cross
beam. No, no, it would have to be a צורת הפתח. tzuras
hapesach. Oh yeah, using the edge of the wall to the diagonal
corner. Yeah, using the edge of the walls. Yeah, you could probably
do that. You wouldn't need the טפח? tefach?
Right, if you did it, if you ran a string, correct, if
you made a צורת הפתח tzuras hapesach all the way, that would
be correct. Okay,
now, one minute,
I'm just checking רש״י. Rashi. No, no, I'm sorry, I just misexplained
that. רבא Rava is saying instead of doing one טפח, tefach, if
you want as an alternative to do a צורת הפתח, tzuras hapesach,
but רש״י Rashi says the צורת הפתח tzuras hapesach for the whole
wall, that would be sufficient. So what רבא Rava is saying now
is three versions of רבא. Rava. We haven't gone up to the
third one. Here's your standard one טפח. tefach. Version number one of
רבא Rava says nah, we don't mean a טפח. tefach. We mean
a צורת הפתח. tzurat hapetach. Okay? He really rejects the idea of
טפח. tefach. That's version number one. Okay? Version number two is no
no, you can use a טפח, tefach, that's okay, but as an
alternative let me see okay here's your טפח tefach as an alternative
it's either that or this. Or the צורת הפתח. tzurat hapetach. Not
only a צורת הפתח, tzurat hapetach, right? Either for your third wall
I don't know, this is getting too confusing trying to give you
all three alternatives on the same place. But oh, for your third
wall you can either do
this one says no טפח tefach just צורת הפתח. tzurat hapetach.
Okay? This one says either a טפח tefach or a צורת הפתח.
tzurat hapetach. Okay? Those are the two possibilities. So according to number
one, it would have to be for the whole wall a צורת
הפתח, tzurat hapetach, and according to number two, it would not have
to be a צורת הפתח, tzurat hapetach, you'd have your choice. You
could either represent your third wall by a little טפח tefach if
you wanted to do that, and if you wanted to, you could
create a more real third wall by doing a צורת הפתח. tzurat
hapetach. Either or you'd have your choice how you want to create
your third wall. Okay? More or less clear? Yes? Okay, you have
those two choices. That's version number two.
ואיכא דאמרי ve'ika de'amrei and ואיכא דאמרי ve'ika de'amrei now there's a
version number three. אמר רבא amar Rava בצריכה נמי be'tzricha nami צורת
הפתח. tzurat hapetach. Which means that you need both. Okay?
So
one minute.
I'm just checking רש"י. Rashi.
Okay. So meaning and according to version number three, it's a middle
point between one and two. Okay? One says you don't get to
use the טפח tefach at all. Two says the טפח tefach is
legitimate by itself, צורת הפתח tzurat hapetach is just an alternative. And
version three says you need טפח tefach plus צורת הפתח. tzurat hapetach.
Okay? Which you don't need the צורת הפתח tzurat hapetach to go
the whole way, but you need the צורת הפתח tzurat hapetach to
cover the gap between the wall and where the טפח tefach is.
Alright? So three versions of רבא's Rava idea of a צורת הפתח.
tzurat hapetach. But the basic upshot is that רבא Rava is saying
that it is not enough for him to have just a טפח.
tefach. So it's a pullback from the idea of a טפח. tefach.
Pullback number one is you need it to be within four to
make it within three to turn it into a case of four.
And pullback number two is that no, is that you need really
somehow a צורת הפתח tzurat hapetach has to play a role here.
So either טפח tefach we don't even mean it, that we really
mean a צורת הפתח, tzurat hapetach, or you're going to use a
צורת הפתח tzurat hapetach to close the gap between the טפח tefach
and the wall. Alright? Those are two basic versions of רבא. Rava.
This means we don't really mean it. There's no such thing as
a טפח. tefach. Here, there is such a thing as a טפח,
tefach, but the צורת הפתח tzurat hapetach is used to close the
gap. So the two versions of רבא Rava are a real pullback
from the idea of צורת הפתח. tzurat hapetach. Only this version is
saying no, a טפח tefach is fine, you just have an alternative
of a צורת הפתח. tzurat hapetach. Yes? Look at the diagram Jonathan
showed you there. Yeah. I don't know if that's a different case
than you're explaining, the way they used the לבוד lavud and then
they used the טפח tefach inside the yeah. In other words, there's
a space. Right. In other words, there's a space between that horizontal
wall you have and the טפח tefach
lintel and the lintel. In other words, the one טפח tefach board
has to be within three טפח tefach of the space and then
they have a
oh they have it going the other way. Oh, that makes actually
more sense because if you're already doing לבוד lavud there and then
you use that and that would get you maybe your seven. Right.
And you still need that so that'll make sense. That'll be your
three for לבוד lavud and your one here is four, and if
you make this then you get your seven. So now okay, so
side, so the טפח tefach plus it closes the gap not between
the wall because I was assuming here that this was like, you
know, this was more distant than the three. But anyway, now this
makes more sense. Anyway, you're right, the three closes the gap to
the wall and then the other צורת הפתח tzurat hapetach gives you
your gets it up to seven. Okay.
I'm trying to see I didn't think רש"י Rashi said it that
way, but one
minute actually yeah, רש"י Rashi says even more, sorry I did misinterpret
it. רש"י Rashi says even more, I misread רש"י. Rashi. רש"י Rashi
says the צורת הפתח tzurat hapetach goes all the way to the
next wall to the next wall. So according to this what you're
seeing is according to right, according to
certainly number one and number three, not only is the טפח tefach
not the reason he doesn't like the טפח tefach is because he
really wants a full third wall. So according to number one
what רבא Rava is saying is the טפח tefach will get you
started, okay, but you still need to finish the whole wall by
a by a full צורת הפתח. tzurat hapetach. It's only number two
where he acknowledges that the טפח tefach can be enough. Alright, so
yeah, but thank you for that. Right? It's just a צורת הפתח
tzurat hapetach closing the gap. And I was thinking about this board
inside. Yeah, right. And then this plus this board, and then well,
however you do that, that was just their artist's imagination. That doesn't
matter. But anyway, however you do that, that then that then gets
you the rest of the point. Yes. Is seven טפחים tefachim the
minimum size of a צורת הפתח? tzurat hapetach? No. Then how small
could a צורת הפתח tzurat hapetach be?
Yeah, well, it's a good
question. Basically,
I mean, you don't need it any less than three you don't
need it because you have לבוד. lavud.
So once you have three טפחים, tefachim, then it's really when you
need a צורת הפתח. tzurat hapetach. Alright, I think I'm going a
little too fast. I gotta slow down for my own good. But
so,
but yes, but what we see here is another pullback of the
idea of the טפח. tefach.
The first pullback was it's not connected you have to use לבוד
lavud you have to turn it into four. Okay, that was pullback
number one. Now you get a whole series of pullbacks which is
רבא Rava saying no, we don't even mean a טפח. tefach. We
mean a צורת הפתח. tzurat hapetach. Or version number three, okay fine,
you get yourself started with the טפח tefach but you gotta end
the whole wall with the צורת הפתח. tzurat hapetach. It's only version
number two of רבא Rava where he says you have the choice,
that he acknowledges that you can really use a טפח. tefach. But
two of the versions really reject the idea of a טפח tefach
by itself, really want you to complete that third wall. Okay, so
that's the three versions. Thank you for that correction. Okay, so the
גמרא Gemara says like this. רב אשי אשכחיה לרב כהנא דקעביד טפח
שוחק וקעביד צורת הפתח. Rav Ashi ashcheichei l'Rav Kahana d'ka'avid tefach socheik
v'ka'avid tzurat hapetach. So רב אשי Rav Ashi found רב כהנא Rav
Kahana that was doing exactly like the third version of רבא. Rava.
He made the laughing טפח, tefach, the גמרא Gemara takes up the
word laughing
and whatever, he doesn't see these two being combined, okay. Anyway, he
made the laughing טפח tefach to begin with four plus the צורת
הפתח. tzurat hapetach. And so he did like version number three of
רבא, Rava, he got you the whole wall beginning with the טפח
tefach but really getting you the whole wall. So he says,
where was it? אמר ליה לא סבר מר להא דרבא דאמר רבא
ניתרת נמי בצורת הפתח? Amar lei lo savar mar l'ha d'Rava d'amar
Rava niteret nami b'tzurat hapetach? Don't you hold like רבא Rava that
רבא Rava says צורת הפתח tzurat hapetach is an alternative? But a
טפח tefach is enough? Don't you hold the version number two that
acknowledges the validity of a טפח? tefach? אמר ליה Amar lei he
said back to him, אנא כאידך לישנא דרבא סבירא לי, ana k'itishana
d'Rava svira li, no I hold like version number three of רבא,
Rava, דאמר רבא צריכה נמי צורת הפתח, d'amar Rava tzericha nami tzurat
hapetach, that the טפח tefach isn't enough, you gotta add the צורת
הפתח tzurat hapetach to it. Therefore even though I started with a
טפח, tefach, I had to do a whole צורת הפתח. tzurat hapetach.
I will point out by the way that if you're saying version
number three, then you basically are saying there's no חידוש chiddush of
the טפח. tefach. Right? There's no חידוש chiddush of the טפח. tefach.
צורת הפתח tzurat hapetach according to normal הלכות halachot is a wall.
If you've got your טפח, tefach, whether it's combined or whether it's
using לבוד, lavud, that's all part of normal הלכות halachot of a
wall. So without any special חידוש chiddush of a טפח, tefach, if
you're doing version number three, this in classic הלכה, halachah, like in
שבת הלכה, Shabbat halachah, this would all be considered a wall. So
there's really no חידוש chiddush of a טפח. tefach. So whether it's
version one or version three of רבא, Rava, it is basically rejecting
the idea of a טפח tefach by itself and saying you really
need a full third wall. Okay, so that's a fascinating pullback from
this idea of a טפח. tefach. Alright, so let's take a look
now. גמרא Gemara says the
following. שתיים כהלכתן. Shtaim k'hilchatan. Alright, two in the normal way. אמר
רבא וכן לשבת. Amar Rava: v'chein l'Shabbat. By the way, although two
and a little bit, the same way it works for סוכה, Sukkah,
it'll work for שבת. Shabbat. מיגו דהוי דופן לעניין סוכה הוי דופן
לעניין שבת. Migo d'havei dofen l'inyan Sukkah havei dofen l'inyan Shabbat.
Since this works for סוכה, Sukkah, it'll work for שבת. Shabbat. Now
the funny thing is רבא Rava דפקא dafka after saying above in
two out of three of the versions that it doesn't really work
in any special way for סוכה. Sukkah. So some switch the גרסא
girsa here to רבה, Rabbah, okay, because רבא Rava has basically rejected
the idea of טפח tefach really working. But so let's have it
be רבה. Rabbah. רבה Rabbah says if it works for סוכה Sukkah
it works for שבת. Shabbat. So let's get rid of the whole
צורת הפתח tzurat hapetach idea and go back to our normal case
of this plus a טפח, tefach, okay, let's even give the טפח
tefach with לבוד. lavud. It doesn't matter. Okay, now here the question
is you want to carry in this space on שבת. Shabbat. Can
you do it? Well no, by שבת Shabbat you need three walls,
even the beginning of a fourth wall, you shouldn't be able to
carry in that space for שבת. Shabbat. But what if it's שבת
סוכות? Shabbat Sukkot? Ah! So then if it's שבת סוכות Shabbat Sukkot
and you're in your סוכה Sukkah and your סוכה Sukkah looks like
that, since for the הלכות halachot of סוכה Sukkah the תורה Torah
has recognized this as a third wall and has recognized this as
a סוכה, Sukkah, so for the הלכות halachot of שבת Shabbat you're
allowed to carry in that space as well. Okay, that's a very
strange and interesting idea that once in one category it's recognized as
a wall, as long as right now that category is operative, it's
שבת סוכות, Shabbat Sukkot, it'll work even for שבת. Shabbat. הוי דופן
לעניין שבת. havei dofen l'inyan Shabbat. איתביה אביי, Eitvei Abaye, אביי Abaye
asked this, ומי אמרינן מיגו, umi amrinan migo, do we say since?
Just because it works one way it works the other way? והתניא,
vehatanya, we taught in a ברייתא, Barisa, דופן סוכה כדופן שבת, dopen
suka k'dopen Shabbos, the laws of the walls of סוכה suka are
the same laws as the laws of שבת Shabbos walls, ובלבד שלא
יהא בין קנה לחברו שלושה טפחים, uvilvad shelo yehei bein kaneh l'chavero
shelosha tefachim, as long as there is not between one post and
the other one three טפחים. tefachim. Meaning, this is exactly the question
that you were asking, that by שבת Shabbos you can create a
whole wall out of posts, okay, and that's a wall, as long
as there's less than three between each one of these, you use
לבוד lavud and it's like you have a whole wall. Similarly, you
can create a whole wall out of horizontal strings, okay, as long
as there's less than three. That we know works for שבת, Shabbos,
so saying it works for שבת, Shabbos, then it certainly works for
סוכה. suka. That is a legitimate wall for שבת Shabbos and for
סוכה. suka. דופן סוכה כדופן שבת ובלבד שלא יהא בין קנה לחברו
שלושה טפחים. dopen suka k'dopen Shabbos uvilvad shelo yehei bein kaneh l'chavero
shelosha tefachim. ויתירה שבת על הסוכה. v'yesera Shabbos al haSuka. Now שבת
Shabbos has a greater demand than סוכה suka in the following way:
ששבת אינה ניתרת אלא בעומד מרובה על הפרוץ. sheShabbos einah niteres ela
b'omed merubeh al haparutz. By שבת Shabbos the space has to be
mostly covered. The עומד, omed, the standing part of the wall, the
actual physical part of the wall, has to be greater than the
breaks in the wall. מה שאין כן בסוכה, ma she'ein kein b'Suka,
which isn't true by סוכה. suka. Now first let me clarify. Here,
this is not considered to be a break. Anything within three is
considered to be completely closed, okay? So that's you can have the
whole thing like that even though most of it is open air
space. Since you say לבוד, lavud, it's like it's all closed, the
fact that it's open air doesn't matter. But let's say what you
have by שבת Shabbos is you've got your walls, but your walls
have breaks in them. You've got your walls here, let's say five
טפחים. tefachim. You've got walls and there are various breaks in your
walls. Is that a kosher wall for שבת Shabbos purposes? So the
הלכה halacha is, it's only kosher if the sum total of, right,
A, if the sum total of the עומד omed of the real
wall or the לבוד lavud wall, if this works by לבוד lavud
that would be the same, if A plus B plus C, if
the sum total of the לבוד lavud walls, right, is greater than,
right, the sum total of the breaks. עומד מרובה על הפרוץ. omed
merubeh al haparutz. All right. That's the way. You have to have
real physical or real wall created by לבוד lavud that exceeds the
breaks. That's the הלכה halacha by שבת. Shabbos. That is not a
requirement by סוכה suka because, and Rashi, it might be that you
figure it not just in terms of an individual wall but in
terms of the entire space. The entire surrounded space by שבת, Shabbos,
you know, maybe it's true by each wall individually and then also
the entire surrounded space has to be the closed part has to
be greater than the open. Again, לבוד lavud counts as closed. But
by סוכה suka it's not true. If you have this by סוכה,
suka, right, the actual closed part is only a tiny drop bigger
than the open part, right, because you basically have 1.9 walls open
and 2.1 walls closed. But let's say you've got some breaks in
your wall here. Boom. Now you've got more open part than closed
part. That actually is still כשר. kasher. Okay? Part of the חידוש
chiddush of the פתח pesach here is presumably that you can look
at the whole thing here as closed, or just in general it
doesn't matter that there's more open space than closed space. That's part
of the חידוש chiddush of סוכה suka in the way סוכה suka
is more lenient than שבת. Shabbos. All right? Yes? When you gave
the illustration about שבת Shabbos you said לבוד lavud was included? Yes,
לבוד lavud is like closed space. But where is it measured? From...
say you have a seven טפח tefach space between two walls. No,
no, no, I meant if you're saying לבוד lavud because there's less
than three, then that whole, then that becomes part of the closed
space. Okay. Are we carving out even more special situations for שבת
סוכות? Shabbos Sukos? Yes. What do you mean even more special? Meaning
this first ברייתא Barisa which is כשר kasher for all the other
days of סוכות Sukos but the wall would not be a legitimate
wall for שבת, Shabbos, we're allowing it to be a legitimate wall
for that שבת. Shabbos. Yes, that is correct. That's the חידוש chiddush
of מיגו. migu. Right. It's amazing. Yep. So we're not done, but
let's see how it plays out. So this ברייתא Barisa is saying
both of them you can use לבוד lavud but שבת Shabbos has
a higher demand that שבת Shabbos also there has to be more
actual closed space, including space created as closed by לבוד, lavud, than
open, but by סוכה suka it doesn't have to be that way,
מה שאין כן בסוכה. ma she'ein kein b'Suka. So it says מאי
לאו mai lav יתירה שבת על הסוכה אף סוכה, yesera Shabbos al
haSuka af Suka, so one minute, here's the question: you've got your
סוכה suka here, right, which is more open space than closed and
we're saying for שבת Shabbos it would not be good, but if
you say if it works for סוכה. suka. Once it's working for
סוכה, Sukkah, let it work for שבת. Shabbos. That's the question. Okay,
so it says according to you, מאי לאו יתירה שבת דסוכה אסוכה,
mai lav yeseirah Shabbos de-Sukkah a-Sukkah, that a שבת Shabbos on סוכות
Sukkos has higher demands than the סוכות Sukkos demands, and this type
of a סוכה Sukkah with more open space than closed, if it
was שבת סוכות, Shabbos Sukkos, would count for your סוכה, Sukkah, but
would not count as a רשות היחיד reshus ha-yachid for שבת. Shabbos.
ולא אמרינן מיגו, ve-lo amrinan migu, we don't say just because it
works for your סוכה, Sukkah, it's going to work for שבת Shabbos
purposes on שבת סוכות. Shabbos Sukkos. So isn't that implicit in the
ברייתא? Baraita? It says לא, lo, no, that's not the ברייתא, Baraita,
it's not comparing שבת סוכות. Shabbos Sukkos. יתירה שבת דעלמא אשבת דסוכה.
yeseirah Shabbos de-alma a-Shabbos de-Sukkah. It's comparing general שבת Shabbos demands more
than סוכה Sukkah demands or more than שבת סוכות Shabbos Sukkos demands.
What it means is, here's your configuration, right, most of it is
open, the majority, you know, it's not mostly closed, and it's saying
if it's שבת Shabbos during the rest of the year, this is
not a רשות היחיד. reshus ha-yachid. If it's סוכות, Sukkos, this counts
as a סוכה Sukkah and not only does it count as a
סוכה, Sukkah, but if it's שבת סוכות Shabbos Sukkos it'll also count
as a רשות היחיד. reshus ha-yachid. So while we are saying this
is the case, right, the majority is open, we're saying for שבת,
Shabbos, right, X, for סוכה, Sukkah, check, even okay, that's what the
ברייתא Baraita says. So it says but what's the story on שבת
סוכות? Shabbos Sukkos? So since it says סוכות Sukkos is better than
שבת, Shabbos, maybe it means even שבת סוכות Shabbos Sukkos it doesn't
count. So it says no, שבת סוכות Shabbos Sukkos is included in
here. שבת סוכות Shabbos Sukkos would also be a check. Once it's
working for סוכה, Sukkah, it works for שבת. Shabbos. When we say
this is no good for שבת, Shabbos, we mean a שבת Shabbos
the rest of the year. But on סוכות, Sukkos, this works and
it works even for שבת Shabbos purposes on סוכות. Sukkos. And you
can even carry in it on שבת סוכות. Shabbos Sukkos. Yes, you
have a question? But after סוכות Sukkos you have the same structure
but it's no longer... Correct, correct. And by the next week you
can't carry in it. But on סוכות, Sukkos, okay, you can carry
in it. But isn't this a practical thing otherwise you wouldn't be
able to use it on... Well, that's true. But we could say
that. We could say it's a good סוכה Sukkah but you can't
use it on שבת Shabbos or you can't use it on שבת
Shabbos unless you make an עירוב eiruv around your backyard. So how
do you fulfill the מצוה? mitzvah? Okay, so fix it or make
an עירוב eiruv around your backyard, you know, do something else. But
you know, but yes, obviously, obviously you could say that that's part
of the logic of the מיגו migu is that it has to,
you know, one way to frame it is just like in a
formalistic way. If it counts as a wall today for one category,
it's got to count as a wall for another category. Yours is
a much more pragmatic way. If the תורה Torah would have to
allow you to use it, so it has to recognize it for
those purposes as well. Okay. That's what he says. So now the
גמרא Gemara says like this. אי הכי, ei hachi, if that's true
that you're going to say this מיגו migu purpose, question, I have
the following question. Now I'm going to read you this next סוגיא
sugya according to תוספות, Tosafos, not according to רש"י, Rashi, okay, it's
a little complicated but I'm going to read it to you according
to תוספות. Tosafos. ליתני נמי יתירה סוכה דעלמא אסוכה דשבת. lisni nami
yeseira Sukkah de-alma a-Sukkah de-Shabbos. Here's another way that סוכה Sukkah during
the rest of the, you know, or during the rest of the
חג Chag is different than סוכות Sukkos on שבת. Shabbos. Meaning if
you're going to say if it works for סוכה, Sukkah, it works
for שבת, Shabbos, you should also logically say the opposite argument. Something
that works special for שבת Shabbos should work for סוכה. Sukkah. Well,
what's a case that something works special for שבת? Shabbos? שבת Shabbos
usually has higher criteria. Here's the case. דאילו סוכה דעלמא בעי טפח
שוחק. de-ilu Sukkah de-alma ba'ei tepach sochek. We just got through saying
as opposed to רבא, Rava, that a normal סוכה, Sukkah, a סוכה
Sukkah during, you know, not on שבת, Shabbos, normally you need this
טפח tepach and it needs to be within three טפחים tepachim and
you gotta say four etc. ואילו סוכה דשבת, ve-ilu Sukkah de-Shabbos, but
on שבת Shabbos there should be something special that works. What special
should work? לא בעי טפח שוחק, lo ba'ei tepach sochek, you don't
need the laughing טפח, tepach, דסגי בלחי de-sagi be-lechi and a לחי
lechi is enough, a simple post. Why? דאת הוא דאמרת, de-at hu
de-amrat, you've said in another context סיכך על גבי מבוי שיש לו
לחי כשר, sikach al gabei mavoi she-yesh lo lechi kasher, that if
you put סכך schach on a מבוי mavoi that has a לחי,
lechi, it's כשר. kasher. Now that was nice and complicated, as if
this one wasn't complicated enough. So here's the point. Okay, normally you've
got your מבוי, mavoi, which is the three walls courtyard on שבת,
Shabbos, okay? That's your three walls courtyard. What does a מבוי mavoi
need to carry in it in addition to three walls? What does
it need for a fourth wall? It needs either a לחי lechi
or a קורה, korah, either a beam or a post. So you
go ahead and you made a post. Okay, now he's saying you
have said that if you did this on שבת, Shabbos, you've got
your three walls and the post and you put סכך, schach, it's
כשר. kasher. Now the answer is, duh, it's got three walls already,
it's not something that the קורה korah is somehow doing some special
work. So תוספות Tosafos explains it in the following brilliant way. תוספות
Tosafos says what you've done is you've only put סכך schach at
the front of the מבוי. mavoi. So this is your סוכה, sukkah,
not that. So what happens? Because by שבת, Shabbos, this post constitutes
a virtual wall, fourth wall, we'll let it work for סוכה sukkah
purposes and treat it as if you have three walls at the
front of your מבוי. mavoi. Did people get that? Okay, for שבת
Shabbos you have three, four, that gave you four, okay, so for
סוכה sukkah you get to count one, two, three, you get that
to be your third wall. So that's a case where because it
works for שבת, Shabbos, it works for סוכה. sukkah. Here we were
saying because it works for סוכה, sukkah, it works for carrying purposes
on שבת סוכות. Shabbos Sukkos. Here we're saying during the rest of
the week you can't eat in this. This isn't a כשר kosher
סוכה, sukkah, it only has two walls. Come שבת סוכות, Shabbos Sukkos,
you can eat in it because on שבת Shabbos we consider this
קורה kora to be a third wall, to be an extra wall.
Okay, so it's the same idea, once it works in one category,
it works in another. There goes by the way, Norm, your pragmatic
point, right? Because it's not that, well, we got to allow you.
Here it's not working the rest of the week and it works
on שבת, Shabbos, yes. Do we then say, and because it works
on שבת, Shabbos, we will allow it the rest of the week?
No, that we don't say. But you do say that the other
in the other direction. No, this works, what do you mean? This
worked on all the days of סוכות Sukkos naturally and on שבת
סוכות Shabbos Sukkos you're additionally allowed to carry in it. And it
typically would not have been carrying. But it doesn't work on the
other days, it doesn't work on the other שבתות, Shabbosos, it only
works on שבת סוכות. Shabbos Sukkos. The special thing works in both
cases only on שבת סוכות. Shabbos Sukkos. Okay? So that's what he
said. So why didn't that, why wasn't that listed also as a
case in which, you know, which this type of a thing can
work? So the גמרא Gemara says, right, if you're going to say
מיגו. migo. So he says, הני לא איצטריכא ליה. Hanei lo itztrikha
lei. Nah, you don't have to say that case, that's obvious. השתא
מקלתא לחמירתא אמרינן. Hashta mikelita l'khamirta amrinan. If you can say from
lenient, the laws of סוכה sukkah are more lenient than שבת, Shabbos,
right? סוכה sukkah is a מצות עשה, mitzvas asei, it's not something
that's prohibited, it's not something that has a very weighty punishment. If
here we say because it works for a lenient category, for סוכה,
sukkah, it'll work for a more stringent category, שבת. Shabbos. Like that's
the big חידוש. chiddush. If you can carry just because it counts
as a wall for סוכה, sukkah, we're now going to turn it
into a רשות היחיד reshus hayachid of שבת. Shabbos. So here if
it works for סוכה, sukkah, it works for שבת סוכות. Shabbos Sukkos.
If we say that, certainly we'll say that in this case, if
it works for שבת, Shabbos, it'll work for סוכה. sukkah. השתא מקלתא
לחמירתא אמרינן, Hashta mikelita l'khamirta amrinan, if from light to stringent, if
it works as a wall for סוכה, sukkah, it works for שבת
Shabbos we'll say, מחמירתא לקלתא לא כל שכן? Me'khamirta l'kelita lo kol
sheken? How much more will we say that if it works for
שבת, Shabbos, it'll work for סוכה. sukkah. All right, so this would
work for all the days of סוכה. sukkah. No, no, no, it
won't work for the rest of סוכה. sukkah. Is that the question
now? No, it's only working on שבת סוכות. Shabbos Sukkos. No, but
all it's saying is like this. The only time you do this,
since it worked for A, it works for B, is when the
two intersect on שבת סוכות. Shabbos Sukkos. But the point is, why
did we only deal with this case in the ברייתא, Braisa, according
to you, and not this case? Okay, they're both only working on
שבת סוכות. Shabbos Sukkos. But the point is here, what we say
is, since סוכה, sukkah, since it's working today on שבת סוכות, Shabbos
Sukkos, since it's working for סוכה, sukkah, it'll work for שבת. Shabbos.
So you're going from a light הלכה halakha where the laws of,
you know, where the laws of a wall are more lenient, or
the whole category is more lenient to a more stringent. Here it's
again שבת סוכות, Shabbos Sukkos, but you're saying since it works for
שבת, Shabbos, this post, it's going to work for סוכה. sukkah. Okay,
that is less of a חידוש chiddush because שבת Shabbos in general
has more, is more stringent. Okay, so just because, so that's more
obvious. Obviously, if it works for a stringent category, it's going to
work for the light one. But only on שבת סוכות. Shabbos Sukkos.
But why couldn't you use the סוכה sukkah all through all of
סוכות Sukkos and not just שבת? Shabbos? This one? The answer is
still no. Since it works for שבת, Shabbos, it works for שבת
סוכות. Shabbos Sukkos. It works for the laws of סוכות Sukkos on
שבת סוכות. Shabbos Sukkos. I don't understand because the לחי lechi is
not a wall on any other day. Because the לחי lechi isn't
a wall on any other day. That was the חידוש, chiddush, was
it not? Now for the rest of סוכה? sukkah? No. Since it
works on סוכה, sukkah, it works for the laws of שבת Shabbos
on שבת סוכות. Shabbos Sukkos. It's always on שבת סוכות. Shabbos Sukkos.
I thought the חידוש chiddush was since we allow a לחי lechi
alone, just a לחי lechi to be a whole wall on שבת,
Shabbos, certainly for סוכות... Sukkos... No, that's not what we're saying. We're
saying it's only on שבת סוכות, Shabbos Sukkos, okay? Because, right, because
by סוכה sukkah in general you need an actual טפח. tapach. Yes,
okay, גופא, gufa, אמר רבא. amar Rava. All right, the hard stuff
is behind us until tomorrow. Says רבא, Rava, סכך על גבי מבוי.
skhakh al gabei mavoi. So we're repeating what we said before. If
you put סכך skhakh on a מבוי, mavoi, שיש לו לחי, she-yesh
lo lechi, כשרה. keshera. Okay, which is the case I gave you.
Okay, it's כשר kosher on שבת סוכות Shabbos Sukkos because that post
is working as a third wall. ואמר רבא, ve-amar Rava, and רבא
Rava also says, סכך על גבי פסי ביראות, skhakh al gabei pasei
bira'ot, כשרה. keshera. This is another case where. The laws of wall
is more lenient in the sense that the קורה korah counts as
your fourth wall. So the קורה korah can count as four walls.
There's another case that the laws are more lenient. You've got a
well, okay, and we allow this to be רשות היחיד reshut hayachid
if you have basically an אמה amah by an אמה amah corners
here, okay, even if this is a gap here of like thirteen
אמות. amot. Okay, so you've got a lot of open space, but
because you have the frame of a square, we allow that to
be רשות היחיד reshut hayachid on שבת. Shabbat. They allowed it so
people could use the well. Okay? So now the question is, what
if you put סכך s'chach on top of that? Okay, and it
was שבת סוכה. Shabbat Sukkah. If it was the rest of the
year, no. But I mean the rest of the week, no, but
שבת סוכה, Shabbat Sukkah, can that work? Since it works for שבת,
Shabbat, it should work for סוכה Sukkah on שבת סוכות. Shabbat Sukkot.
Okay? סכך אגבי פסי ביראות כשרה. s'chach agabbay pasi bira'ot kesherah. וצריכא,
U'tzricha, you need to tell me those cases. דאישמעינן מבוי, De-is'mninan mabuy,
had you told me the case of the courtyard, משום דאיכא שתי
דפנות מעלייתא, mishum de-ika shtei defannot ma'alayah, because you're starting with two
real walls, maybe as parallel walls, but two real walls. אבל גבי
פסי ביראות, Aval gabbay pasi bira'ot, דליכא שתי דפנות מעלייתא, de-leka shtei
defannot ma'alayah, but by פסי ביראות pasi bira'ot where you're not even
starting with two full walls, you're starting with corners, אימא לא, eima
lo, maybe that wouldn't be good. ואישמעינן פסי ביראות, Ve-is'mninan pasi bira'ot,
had you told me פסי ביראות, pasi bira'ot, משום דאיכא שם ארבע
דפנות, mishum de-ika shem arba defannot, because at least there's the frame
of four walls, so that's obviously, you know, a bit, it's better
in some ways. אבל סכך אגבי מבוי, Aval s'chach agabbay mabuy, דליכא
שם ארבע דפנות, de-leka shem arba defannot, but by the מבוי, mabuy,
although you start with two real walls, you don't have a frame
the way you do by פסי ביראות. pasi bira'ot. אימא לא, eima
lo, maybe I wouldn't allow you to use it for סוכה Sukkah
purposes. דאישמעינן הני תרתי, De-is'mninan hanni tartei, and if you just told
me that it works, that because it works as walls for שבת,
Shabbat, it'll work for walls for סוכה. Sukkah. מחמירא לקולא, Mi-chamira le-kalla,
that's telling me if it works for שבת Shabbat which is weighty,
it'll work for סוכה Sukkah on שבת סוכות. Shabbat Sukkot. It'll work
for סוכה הלכות Sukkah halachot which is more lenient. אבל מקולא לחמירא,
Aval mi-kalla le-chamira, but if to go from lenient to more strict,
right? That's our scenario again of the עמוד מרובה, amud merubbah, of
the more open space than closed space, which doesn't work on שבת,
Shabbat, but it would work on שבת סוכה, Shabbat Sukkah, say that
since this works for a סוכה, Sukkah, it'll work for laws of
שבת Shabbat on שבת סוכה, Shabbat Sukkah, אימא לא, eima lo, that
might not work. צריכא, Tzricha, you need to tell me both all
these three cases. So רבא Rava basically has three scenarios, and all
of these are only on again שבת סוכות. Shabbat Sukkot. Only when
the two categories intersect can we say if it works for one,
it works for the other. So on, you put סכך s'chach on
top of your פסי ביראות, pasi bira'ot, סכך s'chach on top of
your מבוי, mabuy, since it's now, on the rest of the week,
it's a פסול סוכה. pasul sukkah. You don't have, you know, two
and משהו, mashahu, right? You only have two and a קורה, korah,
or you only have two and the other thing is way off.
So this is a פסול סוכה pasul sukkah the rest of the
week. Comes שבת סוכות, Shabbat Sukkot, this becomes כשרה, kesherah, since these
are recognized as walls for שבת, Shabbat, it works for שבת סוכה
Shabbat Sukkah when it becomes שבת Shabbat on שבת Shabbat itself. Okay?
So that, a wall for שבת Shabbat works for a wall for
סוכה. Sukkah. Here you've got a structure that has, this is your
two and משהו mashahu with some open spaces, and this during all
other שבתות Shabbatot of the year is not a רשות היחיד reshut
hayachid because there's too much open space. Comes שבת סוכות, Shabbat Sukkot,
since we recognize it as a סוכה, Sukkah, we're going to recognize
it as a wall for שבת. Shabbat. And that שבת סוכות Shabbat
Sukkot you're allowed to carry in. And that's what it means, since
it works for the lenient case, for the סוכה Sukkah case, it'll
work even as a wall for the strict case for שבת Shabbat
purposes, but again, only on שבת סוכות. Shabbat Sukkot. Alright, now let's
do a little bit more, because now it gets a lot easier
until it gets harder again. חמתה מרובה מצילתה, chamata merubbah mi-tzilatah, if
there's more sun than shade, it's good. תנו רבנן, Tano rabbanan, I'm
sorry, it's no good. תנו רבנן חמתה מרובה, Tano rabbanan chamata merubbah,
חמתה מחמת סכך, chamata machmat s'chach, the only concern of being too
sunlight getting through is that the סכך s'chach lets through sunlight. ולא
מחמת דפנות, Ve-lo machmat defannot, but we don't care about the walls.
If the walls are transparent, who cares? The walls don't have to
block out sunlight. The demand that it has to provide shade is
only a demand of the סכך. s'chach. רבי יאשיה אומר, Rabbi Yoshia
omer, רבי יאשיה Rabbi Yoshia says, אף מחמת דפנות, af machmat defannot,
no, even the walls have to provide shade. אמר רבי יימר בר
שלמיא משמיה דאביי, Amar Rabbi Yeimar bar Shmaya mi-shmei de-Abaye, מאי טעמא
דרבי יאשיה, mai ta'ama de-Rabbi Yoshia, what's רבי יאשיה's Rabbi Yoshia's reasoning
that the walls have to provide shade? דכתיב, De-chetiv, or he said,
no, actually, excuse me, he started that was rhetorical. What's the reasoning
of רבי יאשיה? Rabbi Yoshia? דכתיב, De-chetiv, the verse says, וסכות על
הארון את הפרוכת, ve-sakkota al ha-aron et ha-parochet, fascinating, putting us right
back into the קדש קדשים Kodesh Kodashim from like two days ago,
right? We're constantly being put back there. So it says you shall
make a curtain, a פרוכת, parochet, and the פרוכת parochet will shade
the ארון. aron. So a פרוכת parochet is a wall and it's
using the verb of סכך, s'chach, וסכות. ve-sakkota. פרוכת parochet מ... We
all along have been saying the עיקר סוכה Sukkah, is the סכך
schach and the walls are just some attendant part. He's saying, no,
the word סכך schach is used in terms of the walls, the
walls are also part of your סוכה, Sukkah are also, I mean
are equally important and have to provide shade and they're also a
type of a סכך. schach. By the way, what's the obvious question
to ask? If you really call the walls סכך, schach, what's the
obvious question? Do they have to be made from כשר סכך? kosher
schach? Okay, according to this approach. So he says, no, no, no,
we're not going that far, but there is a ראשון Rishon that
actually says that, that according to this approach, it actually is ממש
mamash the laws of סכך schach and has to be made from
כשר סכך. kosher schach. Or even סכך schach on the top here
because it's דופן עקומה. dofen akuma. Right, then you really don't need
much of a חידוש chiddush for דופן עקומה dofen akuma because everything
is סכך. schach. Anyway, but let's not go that far, but at
least it has to function to provide shade. Okay, even walls for
to be כשר kosher have to provide shade. אלמא מחיצה כסכך בעינן,
Alma mechitzah keschach beinan, you need it like סכך schach and it
needs to provide shade. ורבנן, Verabbanan, and the rabbis will say no,
ההוא דניחופיה פורתא דמחזי כסכך. Hahu denichufia porta demechzei keschach. It doesn't
mean that the, it doesn't mean that the פרוכת parochet is shading,
it means that you bend over a little top of the curtain
so the top of the curtain is like a little bit of
a סכך. schach. So all it means is you have this whole
curtain and you bend it over a little bit at the top.
So therefore it functions a little bit like סכך, schach, but the
wall does not have the demands of סכך, schach, the wall does
not have to provide shade. So let's get started on the next
piece. אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, said Abaye, רבי ורבי יאשיה ורבי יהודה
ורבי שמעון ורבן גמליאל ובית שמאי ורבי אליעזר ואחרים, Rebbi veRebbi Yoshiya
veRebbi Yehuda veRebbi Shimon veRabban Gamliel uVeit Shammai veRebbi Eliezer veAcherim, all
of these תנאים, Tannaim, כולהו סבירא להו סוכה דירת קבע בעינן. kuhlhu
sevira lehu Sukkah dirat keva beinan. Now this is a very important
idea of אביי, Abaye, which is, until now we've been seeing these
ideas peppered throughout and I've maybe been alerting you to it. Different
תנאים Tannaim that more make demands that maybe the demands that the
סוכה Sukkah, be a little bit more permanent, a little bit more
of a serious and substantial structure. What אביי Abaye has done is
he's collected all the different תנאים Tannaim that have more stringent demands
by סוכה, Sukkah particularly in the point that it has to be
more, you know, sort of permanent, and said they're more or less
working from a similar conception that סוכה Sukkah is a permanent structure,
not a temporary. Now they don't exactly agree with how that translates
in terms of the specific parameters. You could think permanent is defined
that way, I'll think permanent is defined this way, but fundamentally we're
all rooted in this idea that סוכה Sukkah is a permanent structure
or at least quasi-permanent. And let's just see a few of them.
Okay, and I know it's already late but let's just give it
two me, two more minutes. Okay, רבי דתניא, Rebbi detanya, Rebbi because
we taught, רבי אומר כל סוכה שאין בה ארבע אמות על ארבע
אמות פסולה. Rebbi omer kol Sukkah she'ein bah arba amot al arba
amot pesulah. We've been saying seven טפחים tefachim by seven טפחים, tefachim,
but רבי Rebbi says it has to be ארבע אמות arba amot
by ארבע אמות. arba amot. What's that debate about? It's that רבי
Rebbi demands that the סוכה Sukkah be more of a permanent structure.
רבי יאשיה הא דאמרן, Rebbi Yoshiya ha de'amran, Rebbi Yoshiya we just
said, רבי יאשיה Rebbi Yoshiya demands that the walls provide shade, right?
Could you imagine living in a house where the walls didn't block
out the sunlight? Right, so you're going to, so that's a normal
demand to make. You want it to be more house-like, you better
have your walls provide shade. Similar, a similar idea, not that your
walls are a type of a סכך. schach. No, walls for a
normal person to live in a house means walls also provide shade.
Okay, that's where he's coming from. רבי יהודה, Rebbi Yehuda, going back
to our first משנה, Mishna, דתנן סוכה שהיא גבוהה למעלה מעשרים אמה
פסולה ורבי יהודה מכשיר. Detnan Sukkah shehi gevohah lemalah me'esrim amah pesulah
veRebbi Yehuda machshir. רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda says the סוכה Sukkah? can
be twenty אמות amot high. How can you have such a high
סוכה? Sukkah It must be you are okay, that סוכה Sukkah can
be a permanent structure. That's another, you know, another expression of this
idea. רבי שמעון דתניא. Rebbi Shimon detanya. Now again, very nice, collecting
all the stuff we've been talking about. שתים כהלכתן ושלישית אפילו טפח.
Shtayim kehilchatan veshlishit afilu tefach. We say two and a little bit.
רבי שמעון אומר שלש כהלכתן ורביעית אפילו טפח. Rebbi Shimon omer shalosh
kehilchatan verevi'it afilu tefach. Right, when we had that, right, רבי שמעון
Rebbi Shimon says three and a bit. Right, remember what the גמרא
Gemara said? It said it protects you from the rain and the
winds. So that's also basically because it has to be more like
a house. So according to one תנא tanna that means it has
to provide shade, according to another תנא tanna it means it has
to be three walls and a bit, has to provide protect you
more from elements in general, not just the shade. All of these
are variations of the idea that a סוכה Sukkah is more permanent.
So right now he has collected the four tannaitic ideas that we've
already seen. רבי Rebbi as it translates into minimum dimensions, four by
four אמות, amot, רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda as it translates into height,
it can be higher than twenty אמות, amot, right? The question about
the walls providing shade and the question about the number of the
walls, three and a bit according to one in order to also
protect from the elements. All different expressions of the idea that a
סוכה is more permanent. A permanent dwelling. So what we'll do tomorrow
is we'll finish up with this, we'll talk about the other תנאים
Tannaim that hold of that idea and then we'll move on to
a significantly different point.